听译、时间轴：刘巍然（学酥）
我们之前已经讨论过最终一致性系统
So, we've talked about these eventually consistent systems.
在本课程的最后一部分 我们切换回一致性要求非常强的系统
For the last section, let's switch back to very strongly consistent systems.
我想向大家介绍的是
And what I'd like to tell you about
由谷歌开发的一个非常有趣的数据库系统 叫做Spanner
is a very interesting database system developed by Google, called Spanner.
这是一个规模非常大的数据库系统
This is a very large-scale database system.
是一个用来处理大规模数据的数据库系统
It's intended to be used with huge amounts of data,
上百万个节点分布在世界各地
with millions of nodes spread all around the globe,
尽管系统规模巨大
and nevertheless, despite this huge scale,
此数据库仍然期望满足强一致性
we want to achieve very strong consistency properties in this database.
特别地 此数据库期望满足经典的一致性模型
In particular, the classic that we've seen.
我们希望满足可串行事务隔离 这是我们能得到的最强隔离级别
We want serializable transaction isolation, the strongest isolation we can get.
我们希望读和写满足线性一致性
We want linearizability for reads and writes,
这意味着我们总能看到最新的写入值
that means we're always going to see an up-to-date value from any value written.
进一步 我们希望系统支持分片
Moreover, we need to support sharding,
这意味着如此大规模的数据
which means that this huge amount of data,
远远超过了单个节点的存储能力
which is far too much to store on a single node,
我们必须将数据切分成子集 每个节点存储数据子集的一个副本
we have to split into subsets of data, each node has a replica of a subset of the data,
这样一来 你可以在所有不同的节点实现数据的分布式存储
so that now, you can distribute the data across all of these different nodes.
但这也意味着
But this now means that
有的事务可能需要在多个节点上读取和写入数据
you might have a transaction that needs to read and write data on multiple nodes.
如果出现类似的分布式事务 我们需要原子提交
And if this happens, distribute a transaction like this, we need atomic commit
使得此事务引发的任何数据修改
so that any changes made by a transaction
或者被其他所有节点提交 或者被其他所有节点中止
will either be committed on all of the nodes or aborted on all of the nodes.
我们希望数据库满足上述所有经典性质
So, all of these classic properties we want.
Spanner使用了很多技术来满足这些性质
And a lot of the techniques that Spanner uses to implement these properties
大部分技术与经典标准算法等价
are equally classic standard algorithms.
为了复制分片内的节点 Spanner使用了状态机复制
So, in order to replicate the nodes within a shard, it uses state machine replication.
Spanner使用的是Paxos共识算法 而不是Raft共识算法
It uses the Paxos consensus algorithm rather than Raft,
但这两个共识算法非常相似 原理也几乎完全一样
but they are reasonably similar, and the principles are very much the same.
为了实现可串行事务隔离
In order to achieve serializable transaction isolation,
我们使用了经典的两阶段锁定
we use the classic two-phase locking,
这意味着对于任何读操作 我们获得待读数据的共享锁
that means for any reads, we take a shared lock on any data that we want to read,
对于任何写操作 我们需要获得待写数据的独占锁
and for any writes, we'd need to take an exclusive lock on any data that we write.
我们需要一直持有这些锁 直到事务提交完毕
And we need to hold those locks until the transaction commits.
最后 为了实现跨多个分片的原子性 我们也使用了经典算法
Finally, in order to achieve atomicity across multiple shards, we do the classic.
我们使用的就是前面课程中介绍的两阶段提交
We do two-phase commit exactly like we saw in the last lecture.
真正实现所有这些技术
So, so far, actually implementing all of these things well
也是一个重大的工程挑战
is still a significant engineering challenge,
但确实没有引入什么新的概念
but there's nothing conceptually very new here.
Spanner有趣的地方在于
Where Spanner gets interesting is that
此系统支持不用锁的只读事务
it has support for read-only transactions that take no locks.
这是一个很特殊的功能 回忆一下两阶段锁定的含义
Now, this is special, because if you remember what two-phase locking means,
两阶段锁定意味着 如果你想读取数据 你首先必须持有数据的共享锁
means if you want to read any data, you first have to take a shared lock on that data.
共享锁将阻止任意其他事务更新数据
And a shared lock is going to prevent any other transactions from updating that data.
但在真实系统中 你经常会面对非常大的只读事务
But now, in real systems, you often get very large read-only transactions.
例如 数据库备份就是一个非常大的只读事务
So, for example, taking a database backup is a very large read-only transaction
此事务本质上需要读取整个数据
that needs to read essentially the entire database.
备份本来就是要创建整个数据库的拷贝
That's what a backup is. It's a copy of the entire database.
因此 备份可能会花费非常长的时间
And so, this backup might take a long time.
如果你在备份数据库的过程中
And if you have to take a shared lock on the entire database for a long time
必须长时间持有整个数据库的共享锁
while you're doing a database backup,
用户可能就不太高兴了
then users are not going to like that very much,
因为这意味着
because it means that
整个备份期间都不能向数据库写入任何数据
no writes can be made to the database for the entire duration of this backup.
这在实际中是行不通的
So, that would simply not fly in practice.
我们必须想办法
We have to have some way of
让只读事务不用锁
doing read-only transaction that does not require any locks.
Spanner有趣的地方在于
And the interesting thing about Spanner is
如何支持不用锁的只读事务
how it enables those kinds of read-only transactions.
实现不用锁只读事务的方法是
So, the way this works is that
只读事务可以从一个被称为一致性快照的地方读取数据
a read-only transaction can read from what is called a consistent snapshot.
一致性快照本质上是一种
So, a consistent snapshot is a way of
在某个时间点查看整个数据库的方法
essentially looking at the entire database at one point in time.
需要使用时间戳来实现一致性快照
And the way it does this is using timestamps.
从一致性的角度看 关键点在于
Now, the important thing for this consistent aspect is that
快照的一致性与因果关系是相同的
it means we're consistent with causality.
我这里的意思是
And so, what I mean with this is
如果我们有两个事务T_1和T_2 如果T_1在T_2之前发生
if we have two transactions T_1 and T_2, and if T_1 happened before T_2,
那么如果我们的快照包含T_2的写操作
then if we have a snapshot that contains the writes that were made by T_2,
则此快照也必须包含T_1的写操作
then that snapshot must also reflect the writes by T_1, right?
这意味着我们的快照
That means that we don't end up with
不会丢失部分因果依赖关系
some of the causal dependencies missing from the snapshot,
类似地 如果事务不包含T_1的写操作
likewise, if the transaction does not contain the writes by T_1,
则此快照也不包含T_2的写操作
then it will not contain the writes by T_2 either.
这是双向的保证
So, this goes both ways.
这就是我们所说的 快照与因果关系一致的意思
Now, this is what we mean with a snapshot being consistent with causality.
这意味着
It just means that
我们不会得到不满足因果关系的数据库快照
we don't have bits of the database snapshot that don't make sense causally.
如果快照包含了某个效果 则此快照也将包含产生此效果的原因
So, if the snapshot contains the effect, then it will also contain the cause of that effect.
即使只读事务在不用锁的条件下运行了很长一段时间
And so, we want to ensure this consistent snapshot
我们也希望读操作满足一致性快照所提供的一致性保证
even if the read-only transaction runs for a long time and without taking any locks.
实现这一一致性模型的方法被称为
And the way this is done is through approach called
多版本并发控制 缩写为MVCC
multi-version concurrency control, or MVCC.
MVCC实际上是一个非常常用的技术
Now, MVCC is actually a very common technique.
此技术被Postgres、MySQL等多个数据库系统所应用
It's used in lots of databases including Postgres, MySQL, for example.
此技术的工作原理是为每一个事务附加一个时间戳 也就是这里的t_w
And the way it works is it attaches a timestamp to every transaction.
假设一个读写事务拥有时间戳t_w
Let's say that a read-write transaction has a timestamp t_w.
此时间戳是在此事务提交时指定的
And that timestamp is assigned at the time when that transaction commits.
随后 任意被事务T_w写入的数据
And then, any data that is written by this transaction T_w,
也会关联此事务的提交时间戳
any data is associated, is tagged with the commit timestamp
即数据会用事务的提交时间戳打标
of the transaction that wrote it.
现在 如果一个对象将要被一个事务更新
And now, if we have an object that is being updated by a transaction,
我们不会简单地在原地覆盖该对象
now we won't simply overwrite that object in place,
我们构建此对象的一个新拷贝
but we will make a new copy of that object,
这个新版本的对象打标的时间戳
and that new version of the object
等于更新此对象的事务提交时间戳t_w
will be tagged with the timestamp t_w of the transaction that wrote that version.
我们会在原地保留旧版本的对象
But we will keep the old version of the object in place,
以防有一个只读事务需要读取旧版本
in case there's a read-only transaction that actually needs to read the old version.
现在 我们也为每个只读事务关联一个时间戳
And now, we associate each read-only transaction also with a timestamp.
这个时间戳可以标识出
And that timestamp identifies
在这一时间点观察数据库时
the snapshot which is the point in time
应该查看哪个快照
at which that snapshot is observing the database.
现在 如果只读事务想要读取一个特定的对象
And now, if the read-only transaction wants to read a particular object,
只读事务会查看各种不同版本的对象 每个版本都打标了一个时间戳
it looks at the different versions of that object, each version tagged with a timestamp.
只读事务忽略所有大于快照时间戳的对象版本
It ignores any versions that have a timestamp greater than the snapshot timestamp.
随后
And then,
对于所有时间戳小于或等于快照时间戳的版本
of those versions that have a timestamp less than or equal to the snapshot timestamp,
只读事务选择最大的时间戳版本
it picks the highest.
这就是只读事务应该查看的对象版本
And that is the version of the object that this transaction is going to see.
这样一来
And so,
可以很容易让只读事务忽略所有并发写操作
this now allows the read-only transaction to simply ignore any writes made concurrently.
因此
So,
只读事务可以在特定时间t_r查看整个数据库
the read-only transaction is going to see the entire database as of this particular time t_r
并在不用锁的条件下忽略所有并发写操作
regardless of whatever writes happen otherwise and without taking any locks.
这个算法是可行的 这是一个非常标准的MVCC
Now, this works. This is a very standard MVCC.
Spanner实现有趣的地方在于
What is interesting about the way Spanner implements this
生成这些时间戳的方法
is the way these timestamps are generated.
为了保证快照满足因果一致性
So, in order to ensure that our snapshot is causally consistent,
我们的要求是 如果事务T_1在事务T_2之后发生
what we require is that if transaction T_1 happened before T_2,
则T_1的时间戳必须小于T_2的时间戳
then the timestamp of T_1 has to be less than the timestamp of T_2,
因为这就是MVCC顺序性质所依赖的时间戳性质
because that's what this ordering property in MVCC is relying on.
回忆一下我们讨论物理时钟那节课的内容
And recall from the lecture when we talked about physical clocks,
物理时钟无法保证这一时间戳要求
that physical clocks do not actually guarantee this.
如果使用物理时钟 可能会出现的情况是
So, with physical clocks, you could end up in a situation
事务T_1在事务T_2之后发生
where transaction T_1 happened before transaction T_2,
但T_2的时间戳小于T_1的时间戳
but T_2 had a lower timestamp than T_1.
我们不希望出现这种情况
And we don't want this.
我们必须使用其他方法
So, we have to take some other measure
保证我们的时间戳与因果关系一致
to ensure that our timestamps are consistent with causality.
一个很明显的答案是 为什么不使用逻辑时钟呢
The obvious answer is, well, why don't we use logical clocks,
设计逻辑时钟的目的原本就是为了解决依赖关系问题的
because that's exactly what logical clocks were designed to do.
不幸的是
Unfortunately,
在这种场景下 像Lamport时钟这样的逻辑时钟实际上也是不够的
logical clocks like Lamport clocks are not actually sufficient in this case either.
我们用这下面这个例子来解释一下原因
And the reason for this is by this particular example.
假设我们有两个副本A和B
So, let's say that here we have two replicas A and B.
用户在副本A上执行某个事务T_1
And the user executes some transaction T_1 on replica A,
用户随后查看事务的执行结果
and then views the results of that transaction.
用户在屏幕上看到了T_1的执行结果 随后选择执行某个动作
So, the user has the results on the screen, then, the user chooses to perform some action,
此操作形成了在副本B上执行的事务T_2
and that action results in some transaction T_2 being executed on replica B.
这里很清楚 T_1是在T_2之前发生的
So here, very clearly, it's the case that T_1 happened before T_2,
因为中间还涉及用户的通信
because there's this user communication in the way,
通信过程保证用户的动作由T_1的结果决定
the communication ensures that the action depends on the results from T_1.
从定义上看 我们希望T_1持有的时间戳比T_2小
So, definitely, in this case, we want T_1 to have a lower timestamp than T_2.
但如果我们这里使用Lamport时钟 回忆一下Lamport时钟的工作原理
But if we're using Lamport clocks, well, remember the way Lamport clocks work is
Lamport时钟要在网络中发送的每一条消息上附加一个时间戳
they work by attaching a timestamp to every message that is sent over the network.
当你收到其中一条消息时 你需要把你自己的本地时间戳更新为
And then, when you receive one of those messages, you bump up your own local clock
本地时间戳和收到时间戳的最大值
to the maximum of the local timestamp and the one you received.
但在这个例子中
But in this case, here in this example,
副本A和副本B之间没有任何通信
there might not be any communication between replicas A and B.
当发生此例子的情况时 副本A可能永远无法给副本B发送任何消息
So, replica A may never send any message to replica B while this is happening,
因为通信是由用户发起的
because the communication is going by a user.
因此 我们无法把时间戳从A传播到B
And so, there's nothing that can propagate our timestamps from A to B,
因为没有可用于传播时间戳的消息
because there's no message that can propagate the timestamps,
我们也无法要求用户主动输入时间戳 或者执行类似的操作
and we can't rely on the user to like type in timestamps or something like that here.
因此 副本B可能无法意识到
So, replica B may not actually realize that
它需要拥有一个大于时间戳T_1的时间戳T_2
it needs to have a timestamp for T_2 that is higher than the timestamp of T_1,
因为没有渠道可以传递
because there's nothing passing along these timestamps
Lamport时钟所需要传递的时间戳
that we would need for Lamport clocks.
因此 Lamport时钟也不可行 我们该怎么办呢？
So, Lamport clocks don't work either. So, what can we do in this case?
我们仍然可以使用物理时钟
Well, we can go back to physical clocks,
但我们必须对物理时钟进行一些调整
but we have to adjust the physical clocks and do some extra measures
用一些额外措施保证时钟满足因果关系
in order to make sure that this causal ordering property here is satisfied.
Spanner实现这一点的方法是使用一个被称为TrueTime的系统
And the way Spanner does this is using a system called TrueTime.
TrueTime是一个物理时钟系统
So, TrueTime is a system of physical clocks
此系统可以显式捕获时间戳的不确定性
that explicitly captures uncertainty in the timestamps.
这是Spanner中一个非常有趣的部分
So, this is the really interesting bit about Spanner.
此系统的工作原理是 假设副本A想要提交事务T_1
And the way this works is, say, replica A wants to commit transaction T_1.
在副本A想要提交此事务的时刻
At the time when it wants to commit that transaction,
副本A从TrueTime请求一个时间戳
the replica requests a timestamp from TrueTime.
TrueTime不会简单返回单个时间戳 它会返回一个时间戳范围
And TrueTime does not reply with simply a single timestamp, but it returns a range.
它返回两个时间戳：最早可能时间戳和最晚可能时间戳
It returns two timestamps, the earliest possible and the latest possible.
因为系统存在不确定性
And so, because of the uncertainties we have,
我们无法在系统实现完美的时钟同步
there's no perfect synchronization of clocks in the systems that we have,
我们永远无法肯定当前真实的物理时间戳是什么
we can never be totally certain about what the current real physical timestamp is.
但我们可以追踪系统中的所有错误和所有不确定性
But we can track all of the errors in the system and all of the uncertainty in the system.
如果我们可以正确考虑到所有的不确定性
And if we correctly account for the uncertainty,
我们就可以确定
then we can be sure that
真实物理时钟有非常大的概率
the real physical timestamp will be somewhere
位于最早可能时间戳和最晚可能时间戳之间
between this earliest possible and latest possible with very high probability.
这意味着我们必须追踪节点与时钟服务器之间的往返时间
So, this means we have to track like the round trip time to the clock server.
我们必须考虑时钟漂移量
We need to account for clock drift.
我们必须考虑所有可能导致错误的因素
We have to account for any sort of things that might cause error.
将所有这些潜在导致错误的因素加在一起
Add up all of those potential causes of error
把所有这些因素都纳入单一的不确定间隔
and factor this all into a single uncertainty interval
这样我们就知道
so that we know that
真实时间戳应该会位于
the real timestamp lies somewhere in
最早可能时间戳和最晚可能时间戳之间
between this early as possible and the latest possible.
现在 Spanner要做的是
And now, what Spanner is going to do is
让副本A从TrueTime得到最早和最晚可能时间戳
it gets this pair of earliest and latest from TrueTime.
接下来 副本A开始等待
And now, it's going to wait.
等待的时间恰好等于最晚和最早可能时间戳的差值
And the time it's going to wait is exactly the difference between the two timestamps.
用δ_1表示不确定时间间隔的间隔长度
And so, this length of the uncertainty time interval, called that δ_1,
事务只需要等待δ_1这么长的时间
the transaction simply going to wait for that time.
在等待时间段内 副本A不做任何事情
It's not going to do anything during that time.
副本A只是继续持有所有的锁
It's going to continue holding all of the locks.
当事务已经准备好提交时 副本A不提交此事务
So, the transaction is ready to commit, it just hasn't actually committed yet.
副本A等待δ_1的时间周期
And it's going to wait for this period δ_1.
等待时间一旦超过δ_1
And once that time has elapsed,
副本A就提交事务 释放所有的锁 继续往后执行
now it commits, it releases all of the locks, and it moves on.
这里的额外等待操作是一个关键点
So, this extra wait is the key thing here.
现在 假设副本B想要执行事务T_2 它也做同样的事情
Now, let's say that replica B wants to execute transaction T_2. It does the same thing.
当准备好提交事务时 副本B从TrueTime请求时钟
When it's ready to commit, it requests timestamps from TrueTime.
副本B得到了最早可能时间戳和最晚可能时间戳
So, it gets back an early as possible and late as possible.
同样地 副本B等待不确定间隔时间δ_2
And again, it waits out the uncertainty, in this case δ_2,
即等待两个时间戳的差值时间
the difference between the two timestamps.
这样一来 我们就得到了真实时间依赖关系
Now, in this case, here we have this real-time dependency
T_2的开始时间晚于T_1的结束时间
so that T_2 started after T_1 ended.
等待不确定间隔时间的目的是保证
And the effect that this waiting has had is to ensure that
如果我们有两组时间戳 其对应的事务存在真实时间依赖关系
if we have these two timestamps where there's a real-time dependency,
则从TrueTime得到的两组时间戳 其不确定间隔不会重叠
then their uncertainty intervals from TrueTime will not overlap.
因为不确定间隔不会重叠
And because the uncertainty intervals do not overlap,
这就意味着 提交T_1的时间戳
this means now that the commit timestamp for T_1
一定比提交T_2的时间戳小
will definitely be a lower timestamp than the commit timestamp of T_2.
通过让不确定间隔不出现重叠
By having these uncertainty periods non-overlapping,
我们消除了
we have got rid of the possibility of
时间戳可能乱序导致与因果关系不一致的可能
the timestamps getting reordered and thus being inconsistent with causality.
这里的关键点是等待
So, the key here is this waiting.
当然 在真实系统中 我们希望等待时间要尽可能短
And of course, in a real system, we want to wait for as short time as possible.
为此 我们要做两件事情
So, we now need to do two things.
第一 我们要准确量化不确定性
Firstly, we need to precisely quantify the uncertainty
这样我们才能知道必须等待的时间
so that we know how long we have to wait.
第二 我们必须保证不确定性尽可能小
And then, secondly, we have to keep the uncertainty as small as possible
这样才能让等待时间尽可能小
so that our waiting time is as short as possible.
TrueTime让不确定性尽可能小的方法是
And the way that TrueTime does this is by
在每一个数据中心都放置了原子钟和GPS接收器
actually putting atomic clocks and GPS receivers in every data center.
这当然会引入一定的费用
And these cost some money of course,
但谷歌认为它们负担得起
but Google has figured out that they're actually affordable enough.
谷歌认为在每个数据中心放置GPS接收器和原子钟的费用是可接受的
It is alright. You can actually put GPS receivers and atomic clocks in every data center.
这就让每一个数据中心都有了一个可靠的时钟源
And this gives each data center a reliable clock source.
现在
And now,
数据中心剩下的每个节点不直接与可靠时钟连接
every other node in the data center that is not directly connected to these reliable clocks,
每个普通节点只有一个普通的石英钟
every normal node just has the usual quartz clock.
每个普通节点将周期性地执行时钟同步
And it is going to periodically synchronize its local quartz clock
本地石英钟会与附加原子钟或GPS接收器的时间服务器周期性同步时钟
with the time server that has the atomic clock or the GPS receiver attached.
TrueTime实际上每30秒执行一次时钟同步
And TrueTime actually performs this clock synchronization every 30 seconds.
就好像数据中心的每个节点
And so, every 30 seconds, there's going to be like a ping
每30秒就会ping一次本地时间服务器一样
from each node in the data center to its local time server.
这样做的结果是
And the result is that
每次执行完时钟同步 不确定性就会降低
every time that clock synchronization is performed, the uncertainty drops down,
因为时钟同步过程中的不确定性只来自于服务器的往返时间
because the uncertainty now is just essentially the round trip time to the server
以及服务器自身时钟的时间不确定性
plus any uncertainty that the server had about its own time.
由于我们假设这里的时间服务器都位于本地数据中心
And so, because we're assuming that here the time server is in the local data center,
而时钟服务器的局域网往返时间一般都小于1毫秒
locally the round trip time to the clock server will usually be less than 1 millisecond,
因为这里不存在长距离通信问题
because there are no big geographic distances to be covered here.
因此 每当我们与时钟服务器同步一次
And so, therefore, whenever we sync with the clock server,
本地时钟的不确定性就会降低到大约为1毫秒
the uncertainty about local clock drops down to about 1 millisecond.
接下来 在没有执行时钟同步的这30秒间隔内
And then, in these 30 second intervals between the synchronizations,
不确定间隔取决于
well, it depends on
本地时钟与真实时间相比的漂移速率
the rate at which the local clock drifts with respect to the actual real time.
为此 谷歌做了一些测量
And so, for this, Google did some measurements,
它们找到了我们必须假设的最坏情况时钟不确定性
and they figured out what is the worst-case clock uncertainty that we have to assume
才能保证所有的时钟漂移都低于下图的这个上界
to make sure that all of the clocks have a drift that is lower than this bound.
它们指出 最坏情况下 200ppm的漂移量是一个安全的假设
And they figured out that a worst-case drift of 200ppm was a safe assumption to make.
这意味着在30秒的时钟同步之间
And so, this means here that in between these 30-second clock syncs,
每个本地时钟的不确定性以200ppm的速度不断增加
the uncertainty of each local clock keeps drifting up at a rate of 200ppm.
这意味着在30秒的时间内
So, this means over the course of 30 seconds,
我们累积了大约6毫秒的时钟不确定性
we rack up about 6 milliseconds of clock uncertainty.
TrueTime持续追踪
And TrueTime keeps track of exactly
距离上一次时钟同步经过了多长时间
how long it's been since the last clock synchronization,
因此
and therefore,
不确定间隔会持续扩大、扩大、再扩大
it has these uncertainty intervals that keep widening and widening and widening,
直到进行下一次时钟同步
until the next clock sync.
随后 不确定间隔会落回到1毫秒
And then, the uncertainty drops back down to 1 millisecond.
接下来 不确定间隔会继续扩大 以此类推
And then, they start widening again and so on.
我们可以得到锯齿状的不确定间隔图像
We get this kind of sawtooth pattern here.
这样做的结果是
And the result is now that
我们对时钟的不确定性有了一个非常精确的概念
we have a very accurate notion of what our clock uncertainty is,
这可以允许我们确定每个事务的等待时间
which allows us to determine the wait time for each transaction.
进一步 因为本地时间服务器使用的是精确时钟
And moreover, because we're using these local accurate clocks,
使用的是原子时钟和GPS接收器
atomic clocks and GPS receivers,
平均时间不确定性实际上非常小
the average time uncertainty is actually quite small.
因此 平均不确定间隔时长大约为4毫秒
So, the uncertainty interval average length is about 4 milliseconds.
也就是说 在提交事务之前
And so, an average about 4 milliseconds is the time
平均等待时间约为4毫秒
that the transaction needs to wait before it's allowed to commit.
4毫秒的时间实际上非常短
And 4 milliseconds is a pretty short time actually.
这肯定比
It's certainly a lot shorter than
不同大陆之间的数据中心往返时间要短得多
the time it would take to do like a round trip time to a data center on a different continent,
此往返时间一般为100毫秒或更长时间
which would take like 100 milliseconds or more.
这就是Spanner涉及的关键技术
So, this is really the key insight of Spanner
我们可以使用可靠时钟
that we can use these reliable clocks,
并仔细测量和统计时间不确定性
and the careful measurement, and careful accounting of uncertainty
从而保证时间戳与因果关系一致
to ensure that the timestamps are consistent with causality.
现在 我们有了与因果关系一致的时间戳
Now that we have timestamps that are consistent with causality,
我们在不用锁的条件下
we get these causally consistent snapshots
通过使用多版本并发控制得到了满足因果一致性的快照
using Multi-Version Concurrency Control without taking any locks.
因此 我们可以在不用锁的条件下执行大规模读事务
So, therefore, we can do these large-scale read transactions without any locks.
我们可以执行数据库备份
So, we can do database backups
同时又不用中断数据库中正在发生的任何写事务
without disrupting any write transactions that are happening in the database.
大家可以看到
So, you see here,
真实系统会通过组合使用各种假设和算法
this is sort of the stack of assumptions and combinations of algorithms
以满足所需的系统模型
that you get in real systems,
这是一个非常具体、应用广泛的系统
but this is a very concrete really very widely used system
在实际中得到了广泛的部署
that is widely deployed in practice.
大家可以看到
And you can see
所有这些分布式系统概念是如何在单一系统中结合在一起使用的
how all of these distributed systems concepts come together in a single system,
我觉得这非常令人兴奋
which I find very exciting.
分布式系统课程到此结束
So, that is the end of the distributed systems course.
我希望大家能够喜欢这门课 我希望大家能有所收获
I hope you enjoyed it. I hope you got something out of the ideas.
如果大家有任何问题 请随时给我发邮件
If you have any questions, feel free to just ping me an email.
在座的剑桥大学学生也请别忘了填写课程评估
For the Cambridge students among you, don't forget to fill out the lecture evaluations.
希望大家能够喜欢这门课
And yes, I hope you enjoyed it.
下次再见 感谢大家 拜拜
And see you another time. Thank you. Bye bye.